Preliminary Inventory to the George Davis Herron Papers, 1916-1927
Hoover Institution Archives
- BOUND VOLUMES (on shelf)
  - Volume VII. Bulgaria
    - Herron to State Department and British Foreign Office. Dr. de Fiori; his return to Germany; his discouragement; Professor Jasink; prospect of collapse of the German Empire; Bavaria's plans; lull in German peace activities in Switzerland; renewal of Bulgarian intrigue for a separate peace; Mr. Shipkoff; new Bulgarian Peace Mission; objections to treating with Bulgaria separately; King Ferdinand as incarnate expression of Bulgarian people; Bulgaria's treachery; separate peace finally to the advantage of Germany; would mean the betrayal of Serbia; Bulgaria intriguing for permanent possession of the Dobrudja; Bulgaria as responsible as Germany; a mistake to allow her extension; a separate peace impossible morally and also a material danger; honor of America demands a declaration of war to Bulgaria; inspiration to smaller nationalities, 1918 July 30 (Item IV)
    - From Dr. Marcovitch of Belgrade. Sent by Herron to the State Department and British Foreign Office. Balkan situation; interior situation of Bulgaria and Austro-Hungary; impossibility of agreement with Bulgaria; Tzokoff's design for revolution; Lieutenant Ivanoff; Archmandrite Stephan to Thonon; Lazar Mijuskovic and Gustincic; suggested understanding with Bulgarian Government; Serbia's position and Greece; suggested concessions to Bulgaria in 1915; Czar Ferdinand a German agent; military means alone possible in the Balkans and Turkey; Bulgaria and Turkey must be defeated; Count Czernin's declaration; importance of the Balkans; Salonice and Greece; greater forces necessary; figures specified; plan of campaign; effect on Bulgaria if America declared war on her; and on Austro-Hungary; and Roumania; shortest way to help Russia; action the best means to victory, 1918 July or August (Item V)
    - Mr. Bland to Herron. Seton-Watson; Lansdowne; enclosing note from Sir William Tyrrell; Bolcheviks of Labour; advocating publicity, 1918 August 15 (Item VI)
    - Sir W. Tyrrell to Mr. Bland. Enclosure to Document VI; addressed to Mr. Bland; Bulgaria; Lansdowne; no intention to make a separate peace with Bulgaria, 1918 August 14 (Item VII)
    - Herron to Mr. Bland Forwarding memorandum by Dr. Marcovitch; anxiety among Serbians; Yugo-Slavs; Greeks and Italians over negotiations with Bulgaria, 1918 August 17 (Item VIII)
    - Herron to Mr. Bland. International finance and the Bagdad concessions; Mr. Shipkoff's offer of financial opportunities to America; Bulgarians in touch with financial group in New York; propaganda in Switzerland; all designed in Germany's favour, 1918 September 26 (Item IX)
    - Herron to Mr. H.R. Wilson. As above to Mr. Bland, 1918 September 27 (Item X)
    - Herron to Mr. H.R. Wilson. Bulgarian surrender; interviews of American millionaire with Bulgarians; Mr. Getchoff's evidence; Young Turk Committee and German propaganda; King Ferdinand in Sofia, probably in co-operation with Malinoff; danger of treachery; mutiny in Bulgarian army; scheming of international financiers; Bulgaria-Turkish concessions; Mr. Victorhof's declaration; Austria will probably follow Bulgaria; Mr. Davis, 1918 October 2 (Item XI (and preface))
    - Same to Mr. Bland (Item XI A)
    - Archimandrite Stéphane to Monsieur Boné Maury, Secrétaire Général du Sénat - Paris. Meetings at Thonon; Bulgarian army an instrument in the hands of its own enemies; Bulgarian revolt against Germany; aspirations of meetings at Thonon must not be thwarted; heroic army of General d'Espery; Mr. Tzokoff and Mr. Batzouroff; admiration for France; appeal for special consideration to be given to Bulgaria. In French, 1919 February 17 (Item XII)
    - Herron to President Wilson. Forwarding memorandum from Mr. Gueschoff; his position, 1919 May 13 (Item XIII A)
    - Herron to Marquis Paulucci. Forwarding memorandum from Mr. Gueschoff; visits from him and Austrian Governor of German Bohemia and Dr. Mühlon, 1919 May 14 (Item XIII B)
    - Herron to Sir W. Tyrrell. Same as above, 1919 May 14 (Item XIII C)
    - Mr. Gueschoff to Herron. Memorandum on the Bulgarian situation; not at war with America; Bulgaria's withdrawal from the war; the President's attitude had great influence upon this; plea for other consideration than to Germans and Turks; means required to make Bulgarians march against Entente; Bulgaria a vanquished nation; self-determination; populations of districts to be annexed; Bukarest Treaty of 1913; Venizelo's admission then; Treaty of London in 1913; Media-Enos line of frontier; Bulgaria renounces all claim to Constantinople; as guardian of the Balkans she requires to be strong and have an Aegean outlet; England and America should entrust Turks of Thrace to her; right of self-determination for Macedonia and Dobrudja; paragon of Russia to Serbia, Greece and Roumania; Leon Dominain's article; Carnegie Commission; appeal for wrongs done to Bulgaria to be righted, undated (Item XIII D)
    - Stephane P. Gheorghieff to President Wilson. Similarity of ideas and ideals; appeals to Wilson the man as an architect of mankind; quotations from the Bible; Bulgarian problem under the whip of military dictatorship; Bulgarian criminals and idealists; appeals sent by latter to Peace Conference balked; the President as champion of world-brotherhood; Bulgarian Evangelical idealists on his side; first impetus towards peace came from Bulgaria; danger of new international conflicts; Bulgarian apprehension of treatment by Peace Conference; Mr. Gheorghieff's opposition of Tzar Ferdinand's pernicious diplomacy; appeal for personal interview, 1919 May 14 (Item XIV)
    - Mr. Gueshoff to Herron. Mr. Bullit's resignation; death-blow to Bulgaria if she loses Thrace, 1919 May 26 (Item XV)
    - Herron to Mr. Gueshoff. Disposition of Thrace and Macedonia, Macedonians will take up arms rather than be annexed to Yougo-Slavia; Thrace may be given to Greece; expressing sympathy; suggestion of interview with Marquis Paulucci, 1919 May 28 (Item XVI)
    - Mr. Gueshoff to Herron. Expressing gratitude for sympathy; enclosing Bulgarian note; promise of help from inflential English friends, 1919 June 18 (Item XVII)
    - Enclosure to above. Claims of Bulgarians; note transmitted to General commanding Allied Troops in Bulgaria; also to Great Powers, U.S.A. and Belgium; Balkan question and Peace Conference; self determination in messages of President Wilson; Bulgaria supports manifesting will of people by plebiscite under Control of League of Nations; Bulgaria's attitude (Item XVIII)
    - Herron to Mr. Gueshoff. Herron's wish to hold out hope; has stood out against American Peace Commissioners; Greek annexations by Venizelos; visit of Prince Christopher, brother of King Constantine, 1919 June 21 (Item XIX)
    - Mr. Gueshoff to Herron. President Wilson's promise to leave Thrace to Bulgaria, with the port of Dedeagach on Aegean Sea; his intentions over-ruled, 1919 July 10 (Item XX)
    - Mr. Shipkoff to Herron. Return to Switzerland; end of war in 1918 mainly due to Herron's work; his promises of America's support; Mr. Shipkoff's various activities aided by English and hindered by French; his help through General Franche d'Esperay, General Chrétien, General Baized, General Montbelli and Baron Aliotti; their visits to Kazanlik during rose harvest; suggests meeting at Zermatt, 1919 July 10 (Item XXI)
    - Herron to Mr. Balfour. Acting in accordance with entreaty of Mr. Gueshoff and Mr. Shipkoff; absence from Paris of the President, Mr. Lansing and Colonel House; Mr. Shipkoff's visit to Herron in last Spring; latter persuades him to return to Sofia and get Bulgaria to lay down her arms; Germany thus unable to continue; Bulgaria subsequently quits the war by faith based upon Herron's appeal and assurances; her claims to special consideration; Herron's impossibility to vouch for above statements of Bulgarians; his regret at being unable to place matter before the President, 1919 July 17 (Item XXII)
    - Mr. Shipkoff to Herron. Visit to Zermatt; Bulgaria to be crucified for third time at hands of Peace Commissioners; their faith in President Wilson and Mr. Lloyd George; need of men like Dr. George Washburn of Robert College and Mr. William Gladstone; Herron's inspiring influence in Bulgaria's actions; he should approach Mr. Balfour and Mr. Tittoni, 1919 July 20 (Item XXIII)
    - Expressing sympathy for Herron's illness; Mr. Balfour's integrity at Paris; inclination towards Tardieu's views; conversations with Professor Lammasch; Marquis Paulucci and Mr. Ralph de L. Cazenove, 1919 July 24 (Item XXIV)
    - Mr. Shipkoff to Herron. Same sentiments as preceding letter; departure of Bulgarian Delegates for Paris; Mr. Johnson on Committee for establishing Bulgarian boundaries; Herron's strong moral power, 1919 July 28 (Item XXV)
    - Same. Mr. Paul Olke to succeed Mr. Lansing in Paris; misleading editorial in "Le Temps," 1919 July 29 (Item XXVI)
    - Same. Lost faith in Kings and earthly Potentates, but not in Providencee and Herron; Macedonians' desire to send him to Paris; Mr. Henry White; Mr. Balfour should be won over to undo harm done to Bulgaria by Lord Beaconsfield at Berlin Conference; Minister Tittoni; sending "Reports and letters of American Missionaries 1858-1918"; Mr. Tzanoff in Paris, 1919 August 3 (Item XXVII)
    - Herron to Minister Stovall. Giving particulars of his relations with Mr. Theodore K. Shipkoff; his claims that armistice was signed as a result of Bulgaria's laying down her arms, due to Herron's assurances, 1919 August 16 (Item XXVIII)
    - Minister Stovall to Herron. Acknowledging above, copy to be forwarded to Paris; Bulgarian situation very interesting, 1919 August 29 (Item XXIX)
    - Mr. T. Theodoroff to Monsieur P. Dutasta, Secretary General of the Peace Conference - Paris. Protest by the Head of the Bulgarian Delegation to the Peace Conference, against the establishment of her boundaries; detailed particulars of entire geographical and historical situation, 1919 September 2 (Item XXX)
    - The Bulgarian Peace Delegation to President Wilson. Protest against the project peace treaty; territorial, national, economical and cultured rights of the Bulgarian people; exodus of 100,000 emigrants imminent; Moravia; Congress of Berlin in 1878 and of Bukarest in 1913; conditions must be mitigated; territorial clauses effaced; war debt modified; autonomy to Macedonia, Thrace and Dobroudja; professional army replaced by conscription; cattle to be paid in silver; international commissions to be imposed only if Bulgaria does not keep to her contract, 1919 September (approximately) (Item XXXI)
    - Statement presented to British Foreign Office. Request for Herron to undertake initiation of rapprochement between Bulgaria and Roumania and possible extension to Hungary; if Sultan remains in Constantinople and Turkish Government passes under British protection, rapprochement may be extended to Turkey, 1919 September 6 (Item XXXII)
    - Herron to The President. Felicitations at stand taken regarding Thrace and Bulgaria; peace and prosperity of Balkans; Bulgaria's response to Herron's appeal to trust in the President's consideration, 1919 September 8 (Item XXXIII)
    - Herron to Mr. Shipkoff. Failure of Peace Conference due to grasping attitude of all nationalities; mutual understanding and humanitarian aims required; problem lies in the future; moral initiative tending to the spiritual, intellectual and social enlightenment of Europe as a whole; Bulgaria's opportunity; reference to Ireland; international politics and economics; institute for such; suggestion of Professor G. Murray, self, Professors Lammasch and Foerster and Professors Borgese and Salvemmini; schedule for sessions; divine opportunity, 1919 September 8 (Item XXIV-ante)
    - Mr. Shipkoff to Herron. Expressing appreciation for cable to The President; faith in the triumph of right and justice, England and America; fear of Paris Treaty being like Bukarest Treaty; supporting suggestion of preceding letter; giving thanks for book "The Greater War," 1919 September 9 (Item XXXIV)
    - Herron to Mr. Shipkoff. Enclosing additional copies of Document XXXIV-ante; overcharge of Telegraph Bureau; salvation must come to Europe and Western Asia through Bulgaria; visit from Professor Stephanove, 1919 September 10 (Item XXXV)
    - Herron to Colonel House. Formation of Macedonian National Committee; peace of Balkans and mayhap Europe depends upon an independent Macedonia; Bulgarian renunciations; various enclosures, 1919 September 13 (Item XXXVI)
    - Mr. Stephen Bonsal to Herron. Acknowledging above for Colonel House, 1919 September 18 (Item XXXVI A)
    - Herron to Mr. Shipkoff. Herron's various activities for Bulgaria; appeal made in spring 1918; his then greater sympathy for Serbia and final convictions that Bulgaria's best men had striven to have her on the side of Allies, but efforts defeated by bad diplomacy of Entente and machinations of King Ferdinand; appeal for Bulgaria to quit the war taken up actively by Mr. Shipkoff; his return to Switzerland with aim achieved and plea for promised special consideration from America; Bulgaria's army undefeated; supported in plea by Mr. Gueschoff, former Prime Minister; conversations undertaken as private gentlemen; Herron's efforts to place matter before Peace Commissioners in Paris; letter to Mr. Balfour and others; to Marquis Paulucci; interviews with persons connected with Peace Conference; letter to Minister Stovall; his favorable response; telegram to The President; Colonel House; attitude of Commissioners more favorable to Bulgaria, 1919 September 15 (Item XXXVII)
    - Mr Theodoroff to Herron. Terrible impressions gained in Paris; President Wilson's principles; Bulgaria's "beau geste" of quitting the war unappreciated; appeal for American intervention. In French, 1919 September (approximately) (Item XXVIII)
    - Herron to Mr. Shipkoff. Mr. Theodoroff's address in Paris; disappointment in terms of Treaty; heavy debt; Bulgaria must take courage and cling to high vision; not rights of individual nations, but righteousness of all peoples; territorial question should be laid aside and spiritual leadership sought; friends in America like Mr. C. Crane, 1919 September 20 (Item XXXIX)
    - Mr. Shipkoff to Mr. Crane. Appeal, giving entire Bulgarian situation and personal activities; in Switzerland; in America; interview with Mr. Phillips and Dr. Nicolas Cyrus Buttler, President Columbia University; return to Bulgaria; campaign against Sir Back Ironside; Mrs. Spolaikovitch; betrayal of Serbia, Greece and Roumania, backed by Sir. B.I., Nekludoff, Hartwig and Cobeco; Sir B.I. replaced by Mr. Fitzmaurice; attempt to establish Anglo-Bulgarian Bank in London; object of Shipkoff's life to unite Bulgaria's interests to England and America; Lord Beaconsfield's blunder in 1878 of dividing Bulgaria into five separate parts; under influence of Bismarck and Andrashi; American missionaries of 1857; impossibility of understanding with England explained by Mr. Fitzmaurice as due to "secret convention concluded years ago with Russia"; her compact with Serbian "Black Hands" who exterminated the Obranovitch dynasty in Belgrade, 1903; quotation of A. Dumas on Roumanians; Serbian imperialism; belief that God is a Serbian; their enforced call from minarets that all are true Serbians; Bulgaria's only safeguard was neutrality; but she entered war on wrong side instigated by King Ferdinand and his tool Radoslavoff; had the German Emperor and Bethmann-Hollweg enforced the breaking relations with America, revolution would have ensued; mission of Mr. Vesnitch to America; fails, but wins Wall Street financiers; America's aims; tribute to Herron; Professor Lammasch and attempt for Austrian separate peace; various meetings at Herron's house; understandings ending in laying down of arms of two Bulgarian divisions at Dobropolé; only morally conquered by President Wilson's principles; details of special consideration; basis for political credo; Georges Bonsquet's lectures on Bulgaria' quotations; modern Bulgaria is offspring of America; aspirations of national union, 1919 September 23 (Item XL)
    - Herron to Mr. Crane. Various enclosures relative to Bulgarian situation; future of the Balkans; appeal to use influence with President to modify Bulgarian Treaty so as to leave her her Aegean Coast, 1919 September 25 (Item XLI)
    - Herron to Mr. Shipkoff. Introducing Miss Balch, head of "Ligue Internationale de Femmes pour la Paix et la Liberté," 1919 September 26 (Item XLII)
    - Herron to Colonel House. Enclosing Document XXXVII, 1919 September 29 (Item XLIII)
    - Herron to The President. Telegram of 8th September repeated by letter; effort to reconcile Bulgarians to Treaty, 1919 September 29 (Item XLIV)
    - Mr. Shipkoff to Herron. Visit from Mr. Gueshoff; also from Mr. Tzokoff; departure for Berne; Clémenceau's prominence over Wilson and Lloyd George at Peace Conference; article by Jean Debut; departure of Colonel House, 1919 October 6 (Item XLV)
    - Herron to Major Langley. Meeting of Bulgarian Peace Delegation; interview with Mr. Shipkoff, 1919 October 7 (Item XLVI)
    - Mr. Shipkoff to Herron. Various articles; Mr. Venizelos perverser of historical facts; Herron fighting for a lost but righteous cause; addresses for Mr. Micheff's "Le Plébiscite," 1919 October 12 (Item XLVII)
    - Same. Letters to Mr. Crane and Colonel House; Mr. Henry Morgenthau may help to alter treaty, 1919 October 13 (Item XLVIII)
    - Same. Article requested by Mr. Misheff for "Le Plébiscite"; Herron's relations to The President, 1919 October 13 (Item XLIX)
    - Herron to Mr. Shipkoff. Bulgarian counter-proposals to Peace Conference; Peace of Paris not final; Bulgaria's sincere intentions to cooperate with her neighbors, 1919 October 14 (Item L)
    - Herron to Mr. Stephanove. Article concerning question of Thrace and Macedonia; suggestion to Mr. Shipkoff, 1919 October 17 (Item L A)
    - Herron to Mr. Wilson. Condition of health; returning upon Bulgarian matter; various enclosures, giving complete situation; condition of Europe in general; Peace of Paris pregnant source of future wars, 1919 October 18 (Item LI)
    - Herron to Colonel House. Professor F. Hertz' appeal for Austria; also, appeal of Vicar of Bulgarian Church to the President; copy enclosed, 1919 October 21 (Item LII)
    - Mr. Shipkoff to Herron. Appeal to Bulgarian Delegation sent to Messrs. H.N. Brailsford, Sir Noel Buxton, M.H. Durham, A.G. Gardener, Professor Paul Milinkoff and H.M. Wallis; asking for more copies of Document XXXI, 1919 October 23 (Item LIII)
    - Same. Herron's article "Peace of Paris and the Youth of Europe"; appreciation; sending documents on Balkan problems, 1919 October 25 (Item LIV)
    - Major Langley to Mr. Cazenove. Article by Herron for "Morning Post" as Bulgaria's answer to Mr. Venizelos' article on the future of Thrace and Greece's claim, 1919 October 26 (Item LV)
    - Article by Herron for "The Morning Post" entitled "VENIZELOS AND BULGARIA," 1919 October 26 (Item LVI)
    - Herron to Mr. Shipkoff. Meeting with Mr. Theodoroff; lack of consideration towards Bulgaria not the fault of the President; advantage taken of his illness and Colonel House's; Bulgaria's deficient propaganda; suggestion for journal; complete interior regeneration in home policy based on Fourteen Points; Paper should be called "The New Peace," 1919 October 27 (Item LVII)
    - Same. Herron's efforts on behalf of Bulgaria; letter to Mr. Crane; also to Mr. Vanderlip; also to Mr. Barron; desired loan; letter to Union of Democratic Control in England; Mr. Trevelyan; statement to Major Langley; interviews with Mr. Ernest Guy; article in "Morning Post"; various other letters, 1919 October 27 (Item LVIII)
    - Same. High approval of Mr. Theodoroff's protest to Mr. Dutasta; profound grief of treatment given to Bulgaria, 1919 October 28 (Item LIX)
    - Herron to Colonel House. Enclosing above protest to Mr. Dutasta; Herron's request for advice as to his future attitude, 1919 October 30 (Item LX)
    - Mr. Gueschoff to Herron. Herron cautioning Mr. Shipkoff against his going to America to plead Bulgaria's cause, 1919 November 3 (Item LXI)
    - Herron to Mr. Shipkoff. Enclosing copies of his letter to Mr. Crane and request for article, 1919 November 7 (Item LXII)
    - Mr. Gueschoff to Herron. Meeting; Bulgarian information through Mr. Mischeff, 1919 November 10 (Item LXIII)
    - Herron to Mr. Gueschoff. Interview with Mr. Mischeff and Mr. Shipkoff; request for private interview, 1919 November 12 (Item LXIV)
    - Mr. Gueschoff to Herron. Visit to Geneva, 1919 November 13 (Item LXV)
    - Herron to Mr. Gueschoff. Addresses for "brochure" of Professor Stephanove, 1919 November 14 (Item LXVI)
    - Same. Mr. Crane's address; Bulgarian books to Mr. Adolphe Smith, 1919 November 17 (Item LXVII)
    - Herron to Mr. Shipkoff. Suggestions for immediate future course of Bulgaria; request to place letters before Bulgaria's young king; reiterating former letters; suggestion for concluding the speech of the Prime Minister, based on Wilson's principles, 1919 November 17 (Item LXVIII)
    - Mr. Hugh R. Wilson to Herron. Mr. Shipkoff's return; discussed matter with Mr. Phillips; doubts as to any amendments, 1919 November 19 (Item LXIX)
    - Herron to Mr. Gueschoff. Visit to Berne, 1919 November 24 (Item LXX)
    - Herron to Mr. Crane. Enclosing final Bulgarian documents; to be shown to Dr. Dillon if desired, 1919 December 2 (Item LXXI)
    - Same. Enclosing further documents; dejection of Armenians and Albanians, 1919 December 3 (Item LXXII)
    - Herron to Mr. Gueschoff. Enclosing documents for Mr. Shipkoff; desire for interview, 1919 December 3 (Item LXXIII)
    - Same. Requesting particulars of loan for Bulgaria, 1919 December 5 (Item LXXIV)
    - Herron to Mr. Hugh R. Wilson. Visit of Bulgarian Delegation on its way back from Paris to Sofia; men and missions still seeking Herron; request for interest in Captain Eldridge D. Rand, 1919 December 5 (Item LXXV)
    - Herron to Mr. Wilson. Enclosing Document XL; Mr. Shipkoff's mistaken importance of interviews; impression of Mr. Stambouliski; enclosing appeal from Mayor of Vienna, 1919 December 8 (Item LXXVI)
    - Mr. Gueschoff to Herron. Visit to Geneva, 1919 December 8 (Item LXXVII)
    - Herron to Mr. G.M. Reynolds. Suggesting loan to Bulgaria, 1919 December 11 (Item LXXVIII)
    - Same. Enclosing letter from Mr. Gueschoff, 1919 December 14 (Item LXXIX)
    - Herron to Mr. Gueschoff. Letter from Professor Stefanoff; suggesting general report, 1920 January 15 (Item LXXX)
    - Herron to Mr. Gueschoff. Prospect of help from America quite hopeless; terrible reaction; various inclosures; Mr. Hoover's loan to Austria; indifference to Italy, Roumania and Bulgaria; rapprochement of last two; Serbia spoiled child of the Allies, 1920 January (Item LXXXI)
    - Same. Breakdown of health; administrative anarchy in Washington, 1920 February 18 (Item LXXXII)
    - Same. Serious illness; President's stand as regards Thrace for Bulgaria; letter from Colonel House; rupture healed; advantage to Bulgaria, 1920 February 24 (Item LXXXIII)
    - Same. Enclosing Barron letter, 1920 February 25 (Item LXXXIV)
    - Same. Departure for Rome; dark situation of the world; better future, 1920 March 20 (Item LXXXV)
    - Herron to Mr. Gueschoff. Return from Italy; interview with Count Sforza; private audience with King Victor Emanuel, 1920 April 14 (Item LXXXVI)
    - Mr. Gueschoff to Herron. Acknowledging above; visit to Geneva, 1920 April 16 (Item LXXXVII)
    - Same. Acknowledging French edition of "The Peace of Paris and the Youth of Europe"; visit to Geneva; recall to Sofia, 1920 April 30 (Item LXXXVIII)